<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Life on Aki&#39;s Blog</title>
    <link>https://AkikoAkaki.github.io/aki-liu/life/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Life on Aki&#39;s Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 23 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://AkikoAkaki.github.io/aki-liu/life/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title> 空岛之游：关爱自闭症活动随笔</title>
      <link>https://AkikoAkaki.github.io/aki-liu/sky-island-tour-reflections-on-autism-awareness-activity/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://AkikoAkaki.github.io/aki-liu/sky-island-tour-reflections-on-autism-awareness-activity/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;原是以为这次志愿活动会相对轻松，但整操作下来后还是感到了艰辛与劳累。虽说腰酸背痛难忍，但心理上的压抑与震撼感还是压倒地超越了生理的疲倦。究根问底，是这个自闭症志愿机构与我现下的生活经验相悖得令人窒息——医院也是这种场所，它们将自己与世俗欢娱相隔离。10月19日，我头痛去医院时，写下了「在医院里看完了莫言《白狗秋千架》里的《弃婴》，眼前是无数平庸的却苦痛着的人们，头顶是污浊浑黑的天花板玻璃，霎时间，感到自己的傲慢无影无踪了，众生又有什么不平等的呢？ 」我看到了其中包含的是对这世界赋予的悲凉现状的臣服与无奈，然而，当初的我却未能透过这一幅幅苦难的图景看到那些即使如此，却仍孤注一掷地沿着那明明灭灭的摇曳道路前行着的痛苦与伟大的人们。&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;我凝视着自闭症患者——小孩、同龄人乃至奔三青年，不禁对所谓幻想中的美好世界感到唏嘘。最近看的文艺作品无不充斥着对社会缺陷/社会黑暗面的揭露与批评：宇野常宽所著的《零零年代想象力》与动画「未来日记」将九五到零五年日本社会决断主义的消极倾向深刻地反映出来，加缪的《局外人》叙述一名死于社会与司法制度无形的手下的小人物，而张爱玲的小说集《倾城之恋》更是以苍凉的笔锋流露出生活不如意的众生相。相比而言，我个人的日常和谐稳定几乎到了近乎枯燥的程度，于是不可避免地对完美到不现实的事件进行幻想、编织。前些日子我对此进行了内省思辨，愈发觉得这种乌托邦幻想不堪一击。然而，《零零年代的想象力》告诉我就算害怕社会境况并拒绝接受，这种「自闭家里蹲/心理主义」并不能使人摆脱在这个后现代社会的重压下无法生存的恐惧，人们需要做出决断——并非破罐破摔式的反社会决断，而是自由、优雅的决断方式。正如宇野常宽所说的：「为了跨越一个特定的时代所必要的，不是背向这个时代否定它，倒不如说是祝福，我们应该在满怀期待的同时去克服时代的弊病。」结合前辈对我的一番疏导，我发觉到一味地回避最终只能徒留遗憾，而向着这「看似不可能」的方向努力——即使是 barely touching，也总能给自己留下值得玩味的回忆。于我是如此，于社会亦是如此——即使是 barely 帮助了这个社会，依旧是能给自己与社会上的人们留下值得纪念的回忆。观测着自闭症患者种种的荒诞举动，想到他们整日活在泡沫般的培智服务中心内，虽说服务中心不乏温暖，但泡沫外的广阔世界却容不下他们；他们与社会上的旁人背道而驰，与「正常生活」隔窗相望，我的心便无可抑制地万分绞痛。绞痛有多深刻，看到患者们持笔涂鸦着的欣喜感就有多热烈，对非盈利培智服务中心的敬佩就有多强。便是生来不幸如此，也有着，尽管可能是小部分人还在热忱地帮助、关爱、照顾着他们。所谓「完美无缺」的社会也完全是空谈，但所谓「无可救药」的社会也并不是板上钉钉；正是由于有灰暗有曙光，有 disparity ，烟火才会有如此缤纷的色彩。&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://AkikoAkaki.github.io/aki-liu/sky-island-tour-reflections-on-autism-awareness-activity/1.png&#34;&#xA;    alt=&#34;实地照片&#34;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&#xA;      &lt;p&gt;实地照片&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Serendipitously Stumble into a Blossom</title>
      <link>https://AkikoAkaki.github.io/aki-liu/serendipitously-stumble-into-a-blossom/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 06 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://AkikoAkaki.github.io/aki-liu/serendipitously-stumble-into-a-blossom/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I was staring down from my Shinjuku hotel by Kabukicho. The mood here was different from that of Shanghai: although it appeared to be full of tall buildings and bustling with pedestrians at the massive crossroads, there seemed to be a slight sensation of separation in the air. Although this emotion is faint and concealed, it appears to be grasping my heart, having a significant impact on me that I have never encountered before. I seemed to have discovered a new universe and was shocked in place, flooded with mixed emotions inside. I expected the computer could show me everything in the world, but when I was in Shinjuku, gazing out the floor-to-ceiling windows at this scenery, there appeared to be a touch of melancholy in the people and objects around me and even in the surroundings. I observed a thin melancholy and emptiness hiding behind this prosperity, and I had the impression that I was gazing at a collection of people who were dying to live. It was the first time since I was a youngster that I had the feeling I was staring at a world where life was floating and sinking along the way. I had the sense that I was peering into a crystal ball filled with miniature portraits and pavilions skyscrapers being tossed around by an invisible hand, yet all striving to live and enjoying to live.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
